<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>cyrptocurrency on Slippytrumpet - My blog on the technologies that have been messing with me</title><link>https://slippytrumpet.io/tags/cyrptocurrency/</link><description>Recent content in cyrptocurrency on Slippytrumpet - My blog on the technologies that have been messing with me</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><lastBuildDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2019 07:27:33 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://slippytrumpet.io/tags/cyrptocurrency/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>How to make money with Crypto via ITOs and tokens (Part 4 - the final installment)</title><link>https://slippytrumpet.io/2019/11/how-to-make-money-with-crypto-via-itos-and-tokens-part-4/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Nov 2019 07:27:33 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://slippytrumpet.io/2019/11/how-to-make-money-with-crypto-via-itos-and-tokens-part-4/</guid><description>It is possible to make money on Cryptocurrencies, in an interesting but short window post ITO (Initial Token Offering). This IS part 4 and IS the final installment. Today we make our money! I&amp;rsquo;m not recapping. Read part 1, part 2 and part 3 (the &amp;ldquo;final&amp;rdquo; part) to see what we&amp;rsquo;ve covered.
Quite a lot.
And, as for some of it, you&amp;rsquo;ve been wondering about how it is relevant?</description></item><item><title>How to make money with Crypto via ITOs and tokens (Part 3)</title><link>https://slippytrumpet.io/2019/11/how-to-make-money-with-crypto-via-itos-and-tokens-part-3/</link><pubDate>Thu, 14 Nov 2019 07:27:33 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://slippytrumpet.io/2019/11/how-to-make-money-with-crypto-via-itos-and-tokens-part-3/</guid><description>It is possible to make money on Cryptocurrencies, in an interesting but short window post ITO (Initial Token Offering). This is the final installment, where we make our money. In part 1 we set the scene, in part 2 we got into liquidity and market efficiency.
We concluded that it wasn&amp;rsquo;t easy to outsmart an efficient market. We also suggested that ITOs (Initial Token Offerings) showed many of the characteristics of inefficient markets, but we had a few concerns about investing in ITOs, due to the risk of under-performance, fraud, and not being able to sell our tokens, because we&amp;rsquo;re not sure when they&amp;rsquo;ll list on an exchange, or even if they will.</description></item><item><title>How to make money with Crypto via ITOs and tokens (Part 2)</title><link>https://slippytrumpet.io/2019/11/how-to-make-money-with-crypto-via-itos-and-tokens-part-2/</link><pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2019 15:27:33 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://slippytrumpet.io/2019/11/how-to-make-money-with-crypto-via-itos-and-tokens-part-2/</guid><description>It is possible to make money on Cryptocurrencies, in an interesting but short window post ITO (Initial Token Offering). In this second of three installments we get to it! In part 1 we set the scene, and I left you with this teaser - the key to this is liquidity, or rather the lack of liquidity. It&amp;rsquo;s also about information, and we&amp;rsquo;ll get to that too.
Let&amp;rsquo;s pick it up there.</description></item><item><title>How to make money with Crypto via ITOs and tokens (Part 1)</title><link>https://slippytrumpet.io/2019/11/how-to-make-money-with-crypto-via-itos-and-tokens-part-1/</link><pubDate>Mon, 11 Nov 2019 17:27:33 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://slippytrumpet.io/2019/11/how-to-make-money-with-crypto-via-itos-and-tokens-part-1/</guid><description>It is possible to make money on Cryptocurrencies, in an interesting but short window post ITO (Initial Token Offering). Trust me there&amp;rsquo;s more here than a clickbait title, but first we need to introduce our subject. When people think of Cryptocurrencies, if they know what they are, they think of Bitcoin first, and maybe the altcoins, of which there are many, such as Litecoin and Ethereum, to name just two.</description></item></channel></rss>