<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>3dprinting on Slippytrumpet - My blog on the technologies that have been messing with me</title><link>https://slippytrumpet.io/tags/3dprinting/</link><description>Recent content in 3dprinting on Slippytrumpet - My blog on the technologies that have been messing with me</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><lastBuildDate>Tue, 05 Dec 2017 23:05:39 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://slippytrumpet.io/tags/3dprinting/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Octogon G-Code File Uploader</title><link>https://slippytrumpet.io/2017/12/octogon-gcode-file-uploader/</link><pubDate>Tue, 05 Dec 2017 23:05:39 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://slippytrumpet.io/2017/12/octogon-gcode-file-uploader/</guid><description>An automatic file upload utility for OctoPrint Octogon is a simple command line utility which will monitor a single folder on your local file system for the addition/modification of .stl and .gcode extension files and automatically copy them to OctoPrint so they appear in your files list.
Why? My 3D Printer is right next to me at the moment. But getting files onto it, configuring it, and monitoring it, are jobs that are a bit painful in this wireless age.</description></item><item><title>3D Printing a Racing Drone</title><link>https://slippytrumpet.io/2017/11/3d-printed-drone-build/</link><pubDate>Thu, 30 Nov 2017 21:34:28 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://slippytrumpet.io/2017/11/3d-printed-drone-build/</guid><description>We wanted to build a racing drone on a 3D printed frame Pictured: Completed build
And I wanted to document it here - the build; the programming bit; the learning to fly bit..
But then we got into it. And I soon realised 3D printing the chassis/frame was actually going to be the easy bit.
Drones builds are a massive topic - when you&amp;rsquo;re starting out. Involved, time consuming, but hugely rewarding, is the best way I can sum it up.</description></item><item><title>3D Printing. Learnings shared</title><link>https://slippytrumpet.io/2017/05/3d-printing-learnings-shared/</link><pubDate>Thu, 18 May 2017 19:57:59 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://slippytrumpet.io/2017/05/3d-printing-learnings-shared/</guid><description>Pictured: Pump mount.
So&amp;hellip; I have a Prusa Original Mk2 3D Printer. Learnings specific to this machine, though I expect you could generalise much of this. 1) Prusa Original Mk2 is a great product. Mine was a kit. I built it over 4 evenings, and on the few occasions I&amp;rsquo;ve contacted support, they&amp;rsquo;ve been great.
2) You can spend thousands on a 3D printer. Don&amp;rsquo;t. Prusa is reasonable cost for its ability.</description></item></channel></rss>