<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>slippytrumpet.io</title>
    <link>https://slippytrumpet.io/tags/3dprinting/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on slippytrumpet.io</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <atom:link href="https://slippytrumpet.io/tags/3dprinting/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Octogon G-Code File Uploader</title>
      <link>https://slippytrumpet.io/posts/octogon-gcode-file-uploader/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Dec 2017 23:05:39 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://slippytrumpet.io/posts/octogon-gcode-file-uploader/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;an-automatic-file-upload-utility-for-octoprint&#34;&gt;An automatic file upload utility for OctoPrint&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Octogon is a simple command line utility which will monitor a single folder on your local file system for the addition/modification of &lt;code&gt;.stl&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;.gcode&lt;/code&gt; extension files and automatically copy them to OctoPrint so they appear in your files list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;why&#34;&gt;Why?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My 3D Printer is right next to me at the moment. But getting files onto it, configuring it, and monitoring it, are jobs that are a bit painful in this wireless age. Everything is done via the LCD control panel and SD card.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So when I found out about &lt;a href=&#34;http://octoprint.org/&#34;&gt;OctoPrint&lt;/a&gt;, a print server for 3D Printers which runs on a Raspberry Pi, I did it. I bought a Raspberry Pi and installed &lt;a href=&#34;https://octopi.octoprint.org/&#34;&gt;OctoPi&lt;/a&gt;, the prebuilt Raspberry Pi image which includes OctoPrint as well as some other utilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OctoPrint has been a relevation. It offers remote monitoring and control of the 3D printer over LAN - and WAN so long as you configure your router&amp;rsquo;s firewall correctly  - so you can view, monitor, tweak and pause/stop a print job, over a wifi connection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/olliephillips/octogon&#34;&gt;Octogon&lt;/a&gt; is a simple utility written in Go. It addresses one tiny weakspot in my OctoPrint setup and workflow: the need to physically upload my G-code files via OctoPrint&amp;rsquo;s web interface. Using Octogon, they just appear in the file list and are available for printing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Octogon running. A single folder on my computer is monitored. Any new or modified &lt;code&gt;.gcode&lt;/code&gt;and &lt;code&gt;.stl&lt;/code&gt; files saved into that folder are copied over to OctoPrint automatically using SSH. Save a file locally, and it&amp;rsquo;s almost immediately available on the Raspberry Pi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using it is simple. In most cases the only command line option needed to run the program is the password &lt;code&gt;-p&lt;/code&gt; flag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, you can start Octogon monitoring the current folder like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;$ octogon -p sshpasswordtoraspberrypi
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;download-octogon&#34;&gt;Download Octogon&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can checkout the documentation and source code, as well as download compiled binaries for Linux and Mac, &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/olliephillips/octogon&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately the Windows build currently doesn&amp;rsquo;t work - the file monitoring is not reliable - and I&amp;rsquo;ll look into this in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3D Printing a Racing Drone</title>
      <link>https://slippytrumpet.io/posts/3d-printed-drone-build/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Nov 2017 21:34:28 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://slippytrumpet.io/posts/3d-printed-drone-build/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;we-wanted-to-build-a-racing-drone-on-a-3d-printed-frame&#34;&gt;We wanted to build a racing drone on a 3D printed frame&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://slippytrumpet.io/images/drone.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;alt text&#34; title=&#34;Completed build&#34; /&gt;
Pictured: Completed build&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And I wanted to document it here - the build; the programming bit; the learning to fly bit..&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then we got into it. And I soon realised 3D printing the chassis/frame was actually going to be the easy bit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Drones builds are a massive topic - when you&amp;rsquo;re starting out. Involved, time consuming, but hugely rewarding, is the best way I can sum it up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To document the build process and programming process would be a massive undertaking, and there&amp;rsquo;s plenty of info on the Internet already.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, all we have in this post is a single video and a couple of images. The video shows off our completed drone in flight!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;div style=&#34;position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; padding-top: 30px; height: 0; overflow: hidden;&#34;&gt;
  &lt;iframe src=&#34;//www.youtube.com/embed/KYvZi5S-MPE&#34; style=&#34;position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%;&#34; allowfullscreen frameborder=&#34;0&#34;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;br/&gt;
This image is the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thingiverse.com/thing:629338&#34;&gt;Peon 230 frame&lt;/a&gt; we printed for the frame. You can get it on Thingiverse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://thingiverse-production-new.s3.amazonaws.com/renders/37/d1/c6/95/aa/IMG_0151_preview_featured.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;alt text&#34; title=&#34;Peon 230 - Quadcopter&#34; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3D printing the frame has one major benefit - you break a part you can just print another. Even with fairly high infills we&amp;rsquo;ve broken every piece but three of the arms while learning to fly it - the worst damage when I hit a tree - and whilst it takes a bit of time to reprint the parts, it&amp;rsquo;s better than buying new frames!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-you-need&#34;&gt;What you need&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the parts we sourced via Ebay, and in most cases the prices of items direct from Asia were too attractive to ignore. However, one downside is that lead times for delivery are quite lengthy. In some cases our build was held up by 3 weeks waiting for a particular part.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;ll find some variations on this parts list as some components can be sourced that perform more than one role, but this is what we used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Overlander 3S 1600mAh &lt;sup&gt;35&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;65&lt;/sub&gt; battery - under £15.00&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Radient Reflex 2-3S Charger - under £15.00&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4 BlHeli-S Speed controllers (ESC) - £9.00 each&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4 Emax 2206 1900 kv motord - under £7.00 each&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Matex PDB-XT60 Power Distribution Board - £3.19&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Naze32 Acro Revision 6 Flight Controller - £8.55&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;LED lights (4 strips) - £2.39&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;10 pack of 40 mm blue annodised standoffs - £3.71&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tarot TL150F3 S.BUS 8 Channel Receiver - £6.39&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bulk pack Screws/Nuts -  under £3.00&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;5 pack Eachine Battery Tie Down Straps - £2.35&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Heat Shrink (various) - under £4.00&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;summary&#34;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This post isn&amp;rsquo;t the detailed one I&amp;rsquo;d planned, I simply don&amp;rsquo;t have the time to do the subject proper justice. But feel free ask me stuff - if I can help I will.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>3D Printing. Learnings shared</title>
      <link>https://slippytrumpet.io/posts/3d-printing-learnings-shared/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 May 2017 19:57:59 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://slippytrumpet.io/posts/3d-printing-learnings-shared/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://thingiverse-production-new.s3.amazonaws.com/renders/20/4b/b7/7b/2d/290f686d06ad5516adbf22594411ad7e_preview_featured.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;alt text&#34; title=&#34;3D printed Pump mount&#34; /&gt;
Picture. Pump mount.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;so&#34;&gt;So&amp;hellip;&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;i-have-a-prusa-original-mk2-3d-printer-learnings-specific-to-this-machine-though-i-expect-you-could-generalise-much-of-this&#34;&gt;I have a Prusa Original Mk2 3D Printer. Learnings specific to this machine, though I expect you could generalise much of this.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) Prusa Original Mk2 is a great product. Mine was a kit. I built it over 4 evenings, and on the few occasions I&amp;rsquo;ve contacted support, they&amp;rsquo;ve been great.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2) You can spend thousands on a 3D printer. Don&amp;rsquo;t. Prusa is reasonable cost for its ability. That&amp;rsquo;s borne out by the waiting list I guess.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://thingiverse-production-new.s3.amazonaws.com/renders/0f/ab/be/96/00/f56a6cd1de2b9a1f84e5bf135fca885b_preview_featured.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;alt text&#34; title=&#34;SD Card holder&#34; /&gt;
&lt;center&gt;Picture. SD card holder&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3) Filament can kill you. Buy cheap and it&amp;rsquo;s going to smart a bit. Your prints won&amp;rsquo;t stick, or will fail at some point. Your interested children will disappear fast. Turns out, there&amp;rsquo;s no glory in 3D Printer configuration management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4) Prusa filament is great. It&amp;rsquo;s not expensive at all, until you factor in the carriage costs. Shame. They packed a very high quality PLA filament (IMO) with each printer/printer kit - you just can&amp;rsquo;t justify buying more, unless you can order in size :(&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;5) Cheap filament will dement you. It will drip from the extruder, it will form &amp;ldquo;elephants foot&amp;rdquo; and any successful prints will be brittle. You&amp;rsquo;ll need more infill to get the same model strength. In fact,  I wonder if it&amp;rsquo;s actually cheaper at all when all said and done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://thingiverse-production-new.s3.amazonaws.com/renders/07/8c/28/de/58/677d358891418b54373085bacf9778b6_preview_featured.JPG&#34; alt=&#34;alt text&#34; title=&#34;Mac Magsafe Protect&#34; /&gt;
&lt;center&gt;Picture. Magsafe cable protection&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;6) Heated beds are great. I get extra adhesion. But often not enough. More than a few times I&amp;rsquo;ve used the Pritstick - just to be sure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;7) Firmware. Sometimes I think, &amp;ldquo;Why Prusa Original Mk2? Why you do that?&amp;rdquo;. There&amp;rsquo;s a large scratch in the Heat Bed of mine, which happened during calibration - for some reason - when the extruder head decided to submarine into it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;8) Often multi-part models are best printed in separate jobs. This way if one part unsticks from the bed and takes up residence on the extruder head, it doesn&amp;rsquo;t get dragged through the other components, which until this point were printing perfectly well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;9) Cheap filament. Spare yourself. It&amp;rsquo;s your ticket to a numb night toggling printer settings, hoping for better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;10) Ambient temperature is a factor. Cold rooms will amplify issues. I&amp;rsquo;m on a run of good quality prints at the moment, but have to acknowledge ambient temp works in my favour as we head into UK Summer. Noted that I had a slew of fails through winter&amp;hellip; Similar models TBF.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;11) Mitigation. For me.. set the bed temperature at 60c, put a 215c first layer down at 0.15mm, and then revert to 205c therafter - whatever the model resolution. Shotgun approach or your new personal mantra..?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;12) Software. Good software will accelerate your path to making things you&amp;rsquo;ve designed yourself, rather than just printing off-the-shelf models others have made. I&amp;rsquo;ve tried a few applications, and I&amp;rsquo;ve settled on Fusion 360. It&amp;rsquo;s free for personal use, has a relatively shallow learning curve, and is intuitive to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;13) Print stuff. It&amp;rsquo;s often not plain sailing, and were it we&amp;rsquo;d learn nothing. I&amp;rsquo;ll wager, regardless of how much you spend on the machine itself, there&amp;rsquo;ll be some trial and error required.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thingiverse.com/slippytrumpet/designs&#34;&gt;me on thingiverse&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thingiverse.com/slippytrumpet/designs&#34;&gt;Learning as I go&lt;/a&gt;. Show me yours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://cdn.thingiverse.com/renders/18/1c/e3/85/7a/b88a46457e98d32ef92f633f82a1fe40_preview_featured.jpeg&#34; alt=&#34;alt text&#34; title=&#34;Fidget Spinner&#34; /&gt;
&lt;center&gt;Picture. Fidget Spinner&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>