<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>slippytrumpet.io</title>
    <link>https://slippytrumpet.io/tags/databases/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on slippytrumpet.io</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <atom:link href="https://slippytrumpet.io/tags/databases/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>RethinkDB. The end of the Beginning, not the End.</title>
      <link>https://slippytrumpet.io/posts/rethinkdb-the-end-of-the-beginning/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Oct 2016 15:08:26 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://slippytrumpet.io/posts/rethinkdb-the-end-of-the-beginning/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h2 id=&#34;maybe-you-heard-the-commercial-entity-behind-rethinkdb-will-soon-be-no-more&#34;&gt;Maybe you heard. The commercial entity behind RethinkDB will soon be no more.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project will hopefully continue as community driven open source, although the details are unclear - the who and how has yet to be ironed out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From my first encounter with the database it was clear that &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.rethinkdb.com&#34;&gt;RethinkDB&lt;/a&gt; had something going on. A performant document oriented database had to be a given, yes. But the glorious admin UI, effortless clustering, and intuitive ReQL query language were lovely to see and use; the extensive documentation and examples, great to fall back on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, for all of this goodness it was, I think, the team - the people behind RethinkDB - that made the biggest impression. Their knowledge and their command of branding, marketing and community engagement, positioned RethinkDB as a database that was bound to succeed, or so I thought. Like many individuals and organizations I began to evaluate and deploy RethinkDB with my applications - and I have nothing but good to say about it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why the demise?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far there haven&amp;rsquo;t been many details released and I&amp;rsquo;m keen to understand more as I&amp;rsquo;m sure many are. But I suppose the money ran out and the user community and acquisition rate didn&amp;rsquo;t merit additional investment. That&amp;rsquo;s usually the bones of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One missed opportunity - or nail in the coffin, depending on your viewpoint -  was that at the time of the acquisition of Compose.io - a cloud database provider - by IBM in July 2015, RethinkDB was available via Compose.io. You could get started with a multiple node RethinkDB cluster just as easilly as setting up some shared hosting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Post acquisition, IBM went on to integrate many of the Compose.io database services into their own up-and-coming Bluemix Cloud service, but RethinkDB was notably absent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whilst Compose.io continued to offer RethinkDB, I can&amp;rsquo;t help but think availabilty through Bluemix itself, could have been a springboard for growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did ask IBM Bluemix about RethinkDB and was only told &amp;ldquo;it&amp;rsquo;s on the way&amp;rdquo;.  Oddly, it didn&amp;rsquo;t show up in Bluemix until around the time RethinkDB announced they were shutting down as an organisation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t quite know what to make of that. At best it&amp;rsquo;s miserable timing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But looking to the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of the engineering team I understand are now working with Stripe, and an element are also trying to kickstart RethinkDB into a community developed open source project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to get involved, check out &lt;a href=&#34;https://docs.google.com/document/d/1c27S3Ij2WLB_JiUmpIGkbwJOgVL8T7nW0sPz7OJZjro/edit&#34;&gt;the information here&lt;/a&gt; and complete the form. I have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So it seems we are at the end of the beginning, but hopefully not the end of RethinkDB. As a RethinkDB fan and user, to the people behind the product and the community&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Thank you and good luck.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>